Guide to the Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Reference Collection, 1889-1992
Duke University. University Archives
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Reference collection 1889-1992
Duke University. University Archives
1.0 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
RL.01903
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Trinity College (Randolph County) Reference collection materials were compiled from a variety of sources by University Archives staff for reference and research.
Historical Note
In 1841, Trinity College in Randolph County, NC was first formally chartered as Union Institute and was formed by the Union Institution Society, a group of Methodists and Quakers. Braxton Craven became head of the institution in 1842. The school was re-chartered in 1851 as Normal College. In 1859, the institution's name was changed to Trinity College upon affiliation with the Methodist Church. In 1892, Trinity College relocated to Durham, NC.
Collection Overview
The collection contains printed matter including brochures, bulletins, hymns, etc. as well as correspondence and subject files on Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). The provenance for most the material is unknown and was put together in this collection by Archives staff for research and reference use. The material ranges in date from 1889-1992.
Subject Headings
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--History.; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Board of Trustees.; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Law School.; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Periodicals.; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Students.
Related Material
Trinity College (Randolph County, NC) collection, 1836-1990.
University Archives, Duke University.
Trinity College Library Records, 1892-1924.
University Archives, Duke University.
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Office of the Treasurer records, 1891-1924.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 3 Boxes
  - Admissions, 1904, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Athletics and physical education, 1903, 1910, n.d.
  - Board of Trustees, 1893, 1901
  - Charter, constitution and bylaws, 1893, 1903
  - Financial aid, ca. 1904
  - Form letters, 1891, 1913-1916
  - Fundraising and finances, ca. 1900-1916
  - The Lines of the Future Development of Trinity College / John C. Kilgo, [1902]
  - Law School, 1891-1923
  - School of Education, 1910-1911
  - School for Teachers, ca. 1893-1898
  - School for Preachers, 1910-1920
  - Trinity College Press, 1922-1924
  - Methodist Church Conference publications, 1885-1910
  - Taxation in the American Colonies: … New Jersey / John F. Crowell, 1893
  - Important Facts [Brochures], 1905-1918
  - Educational Tracts, 1891
  - Bulletins, 1890-1894
  - Trinity College Chapel Book, undated [after 1913?]
  - Trinity College Hymns, undated, circa 1920
  - Flyers and announcements, undated
  - Women at Trinity, ca. 1896-1920, 1957
  - Crowell Scientific Society, 1921
  - Debating Club, 1917
  - Engineering Club, 1914
  - Glee Club, 1890
  - Sigma Upsilon / Fortnightly Club, ca. 1914-1920
  - Women’s Student Government Association. Constitution and Bylaws, ca. 1919
  - YMCA Student’s Handbook, 1891
  - Report of Grades and Attendance for Aura Holton, 1923, January 31
  - Register of the Workers of the Trinity College Auxiliary of the Durham Red Cross chapter, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer’s Book, Class of 1908, 1905-1908
  - The Trinity Archive Souvenir Edition, June 1904 (includes map and photos)
  - Building a System of High Schools in North Carolina, by E.C. Brooks, 1916
  - Avera Bible Lectures, 1911-1929
  - Buffalo Incident of 1914
  - Coburn Players, 1911-1916
  - Excursion to Washington, D.C., 1898
  - Theodore Roosevelt’s Visit to Durham / John Allen Morgan, 1905 – diary extract
  - Report of a Visit to Some of the Colleges in the South / William E. Dodd, 1913
  - Clippings about Trinity College from the Raleigh Christian Advocate, 1889-1890 Clippings about Trinity College
  - Clippings about people associated with Trinity College
  - Printed materials about Trinity College
  - Index to Trinity College Reminiscences in the Trinity/Duke Alumni Register, 1915-1936
  - Trinity College and Academic Liberty from The South Atlantic Quarterly, January 1904 (typescript copy of editorial about the Bassett Affair)
  - Change of name to Duke University, 1924
  - Centennial Celebration of the Relocation of Trinity College to Durham, 1992
  - Ministerial Band: Bylaws, constitution, minutes, 1919-1929 (Box 3)
  - Oversize materials (Mc 8)
    - Admissions of Women to Trinity College (Durham, NC), 1896
    - Commencement posters
      - 1918 (2)
      - 1919
      - 1920
    - Published list of donations to purchase furniture for Trinity College, circa 1891
    - Trinity Yells, circa 1923 (A94-4)